all right
[Music]
tongue cleaning can reduce the stinky
gaseous compounds that cause bad breath
by up to 75 percent where it's just
brushing your teeth alone may only
Reduce by 25 this is why tongue cleaning
has the greatest priority in the
treatment of bad breath
are there any downsides well most people
do not enjoy placing an object towards
the back of their throats as it can
trigger the gag reflex tips to help
prevent this include momentarily
stopping breathing during tongue
cleaning you can experiment and if the
mint flavor in toothpaste sensitize your
throat to an elevated gag reflex you may
want to clean the tongue before tooth
brushing some recommendations even
suggest doing it on an empty stomach in
case vomiting ensues that doesn't sound
very pleasant but when tongue cleaning
is practiced on a daily basis the
process evidently becomes easier and
less objectionable over time
so the main complaint of the subjects is
the gagging reflection you know also you
know tongue carcinogenesis related to
Mechanical stimulation
wait John carcinogenesis means the
development of tongue cancer these are
unpleasant side effects associated with
tongue cleaning devices
cancer is more than an unpleasant side
effect I mean I know there's alcohol
containing mouthwashes and one might
expect that to predispose people to oral
cancer I talked about this in my alcohol
and breast cancer video a single sip of
an alcoholic beverage one teaspoon
swished and even spit out after just
five seconds results in carcinogenic
concentrations of the toxic alcohol
breakdown product acetaldide being
produced from ethanol the oral cavity
instantly after a small sip of a strong
alcoholic beverage and this exposure
continues for at least 10 minutes after
just those five seconds and yes this
concern extends to alcohol containing
mouthwash researchers determined that
alcohol containing mouthwashes offers a
rather low margin of safety in that
prudent Public Health policy should
recommend generally refraining from
using them okay yeah we know alcohol
causes cancer but why tongue scraping
well animal experiments have shown that
mechanical injuries of the tongue may be
carcinogenic okay even if you could
extrapolate to people are you actually
injuring the tongue when you scrape it
uh what exactly did these experiments
entail concerns have been raised based
on an experiment in rodents involving
the experimental induction of tongue
cancer using carcinogenic
dimethylbenzanthracine a powerful
carcinogen found in cigarette smoke and
broiled meats and they evidently
produced more cancer with the carcinogen
if they injured the tongue using a root
canal instrument here's the study they
cite indeed scratching their tongues
with essentially a little piece of
barbed wire did result in more cancer
presumably because the ulceration or
injury allowed for greater retention and
penetration of the carcinogen into
deeper tissue layers but people don't
scrape their tongues with barbed wire ah
but evidently even a regular toothbrush
can do it this appears to be the study
they side for that but it doesn't say
regular toothbrush but rather extreme
mechanical stimulation though then in
the figure they say was just one stroke
with a dental Broach with a very light
force that did not cause bleeding which
was apparently enough to cause the
cancer to show up about a month earlier
so what was it a toothbrush extreme
stimulation or just a light scratch
here's the original data and thanks to
our wonderful Japanese volunteers I'm
told it was no toothbrush and even if it
was and could be extrapolated that was
with a carcinogen so unless you were
smoking or using chewing tobacco or
eating barbecued chicken every day there
doesn't seem to be any parallel if you
just scratch a hamster's tongue with a
barbed wire every day no tumors develop
and another thing most human tongue
cancers are found on the side of the
tongue and so the relationship between
tongue scraping and cancer has not yet
been confirmed in humans though there's
still a possibility that mechanical
stimulation may be a cause so I'd
recommend taking it easy in this study
they had been brushing their tongue with
an electric toothbrush with medium hard
bristles and ended up causing an
increase in the expression of CFOs in
tongue muscle cells which is a protein
that may be involved in cancer
development any kind of electrical
device for tongue cleaning is not
recommended but even a manual toothbrush
can cause some damage so-called micro
bleeding therefore tongue cleaning
should be carried out gently with low
Force to avoid unnecessary tissue trauma
and just a top surface of the tongue
should be cleaned not the sides foreign